{"tossups": [{"question": "This politician was dogged by accusations of an affair with Nan Britton. The Four Power Treaty was signed when this man called the Washington Naval Conference to limit arms. This man, who appointed the first Cabinet member to go to prison, died of a cerebral hemorrhage before the Teapot Dome scandal was brought to light. For ten points, name this US president who promised a \u201creturn to normalcy\u201d and was succeeded by Calvin Coolidge.", "answer": "Warren<b> Harding</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Members of this group in Shanghai organized a seven-day camp at the Moganshan resort. The motto\u201cBlood and Honor\u201d was adopted by this group, which was led by Baldur von Schirach and Artur Axmann. <em>Volkssturm</em> commonly drafted members of this group, one unit of which assisted the<em> Kriegsmarine</em>. An organization similar to this one that was only open to women was the League of German Girls. For ten points, name this organization consisting of boys who assisted the Nazi effort.", "answer": "<b> Hitler Youth</b> (accept<b> Hitlerjugend</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "An article in the<em> New York Tribune</em> informed the composer of this piece that he was busy working on it, a complete surprise to him. This piece, which premiered at New York City\u2019s Aeolian Hall on Abraham Lincoln\u2019s birthday in 1924 with its composer on the piano, opens with a glissando on the clarinet. For ten points, name this fusion of classical music and jazz, a musical piece by George Gershwin.", "answer": "<b> Rhapsody in Blue</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a short story from this country, Tacha\u2019s cow dies in a flash flood; that story is titled \u201cIt\u2019s because we are very poor.\u201d In a novel from this country, everyone in the central town dies because of the title man\u2019s refusal to harvest his crops. Another novel from this country centers on the death of Ambrose Bierce in this country\u2019s civil war; that novel, by the author of<em> The Death of Artemio Cruz</em>, is<em> The Old</em> <em>Gringo</em>. For ten points, name this home country of Juan Rulfo and Carlos Fuentes.", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "During this war, one side captured Water Works Redoubt and 203 Meter Hill while closing in on an important harbor. British trawlers were mistaken for torpedo boats and fired on in this war\u2019s Dogger Bank Incident, and 600,000 soldiers fought in Manchuria in this war\u2019s Battle of Mukden. After an invading fleet was decimated at Tsushima Strait, Teddy Roosevelt brokered the Treaty of Portsmouth to end, for ten points, what 1904-1905 war between two Asian empires?", "answer": "<b> Russo-Japanese</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A king of this country initiated a succession crisis by riding his horse off a cliff during a storm. One of the claimants in that crisis was nicknamed \u201cempty coat.\u201d The death of Margaret, Maid of Norway exacerbated that crisis, which one of this country\u2019s neighbors attempted to resolve in favor of John Balliol. For ten points, name this country where the Battle of Bannockburn ended an English attack on Robert the Bruce.", "answer": "<b> Scotland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A mounted archer aims at a group of naked women in the first painting by this artist accepted into the Paris Salon,<em> Scene of War in the Middle Ages</em>. This painter of the historical scene<em> Young Spartans</em> <em>Exercising</em> spent time in New Orleans with his brother Rene, leading to his painting of the city\u2019s cotton exchange.<em> Rehearsal on Stage</em> and<em> Fin d\u2019Arabesque</em> are by, for ten points, what French impressionist who frequently depicted ballet dancers?", "answer": "Edgar<b> Degas</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The second section of this agreement was enforced by the Sharm el Sheikh memorandum, which was brokered by Madeleine Albright. Areas A, B, and C were created by this agreement\u2019s second section, which was signed in September 1995. This agreement established a National Authority, which had limited self-governance over the Gaza Strip and West Bank. The recognition of the PLO was the first step in, for ten points, what set of agreements between Palestinians and Israelis that was negotiated in, and named for, the Norwegian capital city?", "answer": "<b> Oslo</b> Accords", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Explorer Thomas Anburey fought in the campaign named for this battle and described the slaying of Jane McCrae. In this battle, sharpshooters fatally wounded General Simon Fraser, and Tadeusz Ko\u00b4sciusko [tad-oosh ko-shoo-sko] designed the Bemis Heights fortifications for the Continental Army. With the help of Benedict Arnold, Horatio Gates defeated John Burgoyne at, for ten points, what 1777 Revolutionary War battle in upstate New York that convinced the French to join the Americans?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Saratoga</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This empire captured the city of Karansebes after the Austrian army attacked itself and killed over 1,000 soldiers. This empire offered support to the Crimean Khanate, leading to the burning of Moscow in 1571. This empire faced the Celali Revolts, several uprisings of irregular musketeers and Janissaries during the 16th century. Following the Great Northern War, this empire offered refuge for Charles XII of Sweden. For ten points, name this empire that reached its peak under Suleiman the Magnificent.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>When asked if he regretted his actions, this man responded \u201cWas Christ not crucified?\u201dAfter being found in a hole by Benjamin Phipps, this man was hanged and had his body drawn and quartered by the residents of Jerusalem. Thomas (+) Gray published a pamphlet titled for the</b><em><b> Confessions</b></em><b> of this man. He was inspired by a solar eclipse, which he viewed as a black hand covering the sun, to (*)</b> launch an attack during which he may have ordered \u201ckill all the white people.\u201d For ten points, name this slave who led a violent 1831 rebellion in Southampton County, Virginia.", "answer": "Nat<b> Turner</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The only independent research center dedicated to studying breast cancer prevention is named after this person\u2019s best-known work, which was inspired by Lucille Farrier Stickel\u2019s reports. This author of</b><em><b> The Sea Around Us</b></em><b> criticized a campaign sponsored by the U.S.</b> <b>government to eradicate the (+)</b> <b>gypsy moth in Massachusetts.</b><em><b> A Fable For Tomorrow</b></em> <b>titles the first chapter of a work by this woman about (*)</b> depleting bald eagle populations due to pesticides like DDT. For ten points, what female environmentalist wrote<em> Silent Spring</em>?", "answer": "Rachel<b> Carson</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>This country\u2019s La Linea corruption scandal led to the election of a former TV comedian. An indigenous Nobel Peace Prize winner from this country may have fabricated parts of</b> <b>her autobiography. This country committed genocide against the (+)</b> <b>Ixil people under its</b> <b>president Efrain Rios Montt, and this country\u2019s northern (*)</b> Mayan regions were hard hit by its lengthy 20th century civil war. For ten points, name this home country of Rigoberta Menchu, a Central American country where refugees fled north into Mexico.", "answer": "<b> Guatemala</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This event was speculated to have been an act of sabotage by Hugo Eckener, a theory supported by the discovery of sulfur on a valve cap. Another hypothesis blames this event</b> <b>an electric shock strong enough to puncture (+)</b> <b>fabric. This event, which occurred near</b> <b>the mooring station at the Naval Air Station in Lakehurst, (*)</b> New Jersey, was caused by the use of hydrogen gas. Herbert Morrison cried \u201coh, the humanity!\u201d while reporting on, for ten points, what 1937 disaster in which an airship caught fire?", "answer": "<b> Hindenburg</b> disaster", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This figure\u2019s birthday is celebrated as \u201cVesak\u201d in some countries. This figure\u2019s mother dreamt of a white elephant with six tusks entering her body when he was conceived. This person gave his first (+) sermon at Sarnath, or the Deer Park, and had a major epiphany at (*)</b> Bodhgaya. This person was supposedly born a prince and renounced his position when he encountered disease, aging, and death. For ten points, name this person who founded a world religion by teaching the Eightfold Path and the Four Noble Truths.", "answer": "the<b> Buddha</b> (or<b> Siddharta Gautama</b>; accept either name) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>The plan to construct the Berlin Wall was titled for one of these objects. Eduard</b> <b>Shevardnadze was ousted by Mikhail Saakashvili in a Georgian revolution named for</b> <b>these objects. An anti-Nazi resistance movement centered in the (+)</b> <b>University of</b> <b>Munich was named for the White type of these objects. The marriage of Elizabeth</b> <b>Woodville helped heighten a (*)</b> war named for these objects, causing the Duke of Warwick to change sides. For ten points, name these flowers, the symbol of the houses of York and Lancaster.", "answer": "<b> rose</b>s (accept Operation<b> Rose</b>; accept<b> Rose</b> Revolution or Revolution of<b> Roses</b> after \u201cEduard\u201d is read; accept White<b> Rose</b> after \u201canti-Nazi\u201d is read; accept War of the<b> Rose</b>s after \u201cElizabeth\u201d is read; prompt on flowers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}